I
you
So the arrays
and as we
I referred to him in
in Mathematica or the Wolfram language.
which is basically a regular
arrangement of data that has a depth D
with dimensions of length d
and such that each element of the data can
be accessed by part indices.
And this is sort of the fundamental
contract that we have
for an array.
vectors, matrices.
and higher-ranked tensors.
So
in Wolfram
For some array A, we have
The array depth gives the depth.
be the dimensions
gives the dimensions. Um,
and
the part, as long as you have B part,
will give an element of
of the array. So let's take
Let's take some examples.
So several
So a basic test for an array.
And this is going to be useful
and a lot of functions you
right is whether
it's a Ray Q and it's either going to
be true or false.
a Q function will be true or false.
And then we can also do
the dimensions of those.
dimensions of this first expression,
or just two because
the last level is not consistent.
And here the level is consistent in
length and size.
So dimensions of expectations.
for two, I get that three-level...
level.
sort of the, that's kind of the idea
a difference between something that's an array
and something that's not an array.
to
So in that second X for everything,
everything is accessible by a part
with two indices.
So I can do that.
Parts just have to be bound by the dimensions.
and that part will always
always work.
You can also test a rate
is a little more useful and you can test
the elements, you know, an element at a
So you can test whether they're all integer
The answer is true.
You can test it.
the depth, the second argument here
which I had as a pattern,
be the depth and
So this is testing basically it's a,
a matrix and vector Q
and MatrixQ are actually
just, they're the same as a Reikyu, but
they just have specific depths, you
coded in explicitly.
sort of syntactic sugar, really.
matrix queue. Now,
Here's the tricky thing about
what you consider a ray.
because here I'm considering elements
like fundamental type.
namely, you know, integers,
or reels or, you know,
what are typically considered scalar.
But you can actually trick a Ray-Q.
and say, okay, I want, I want
want to test
whether that expression one is in
array of depth one
with anything,
to be an element, okay?
And the answer is true.
Um, or,
another test I could do
is that I could say, okay, I want
want it to be a depth of one.
but I want the elements to be
lists
of integers which are positive.
Okay. Of any length.
And that's another test you can read.
So you can actually have list type
or array type elements
of arrays themselves.
as long as you put in the test correctly.
So sometimes that's,
So if you have an array, you know,
which is mostly an array, but the last level
has different lengths where you can use
this sort of thing to actually work with it.
quite effectively.
I think that's a little known fact.
and
in the Wolfram language.
Okay, so how do you construct a record?
Well, I'm going to show a bunch of different ways
during this talk.
a few very obvious ways.
obvious way is with the command array.
That creates an array.
And one all year.
One I use a lot for testing.
things or understanding how command
work and
Because I always forget the way
transpose goes and things like
that. That's just the mental
block I have. So I created
a symbolic array with
indexed elements.
And then you can kind of see how things work.
work. Another super useful
array for constructing
things and putting things together.
is a zero.
This is actually a, this is a
but it's a zero array.
and types of
zeros probably in a
of stuff you've done don't seem very important.
but as soon as you start using content
compilation and try to
to get things to run faster.
the shape and structure of
of a set of zeros becomes very
important. So that's a
really useful one. I can
also make an array
of arrays. Okay.
Okay.
of that constant array
And if I do, you know,
Dimensions of the
that
Then I get something which is
Step five.
It's the two-two or the first
two dimensions and then the two three
the dimensions of this
symbolic array I put together before.
And so you can kind of repeat that.
you can have a repeated array.
which in many cases can be
can be useful for constructing code
and doing things
efficiently.
Another thing I
use all the time is just
random integer, random real,
random complex allows you to generate
generate arrays of different
of different types for testing.
code and so random
functions are
really good constructor of arrays.
lots of other constructors of array.
then I'm not going to go to it. But if
you want to construct an array
which has different sorts of elements
elements
sort of a very common one is table.
Okay, so I can do this.
So this is kind of like that symbolic representation
array I did before, but this is doing
table. And I always
get confused as to which
index goes where.
So it's actually the
the outer index
goes first and then
the inner index.
I'm addressing this as a
So I make a table of these.
of the
minus three and then that.
And and they're
some, there can be some
some cases some efficiency of using
this table with the multiple
indices because it's automatic.
I don't know if it's automatically compiled,
Pretty rarely is the case that it makes a huge difference
huge difference.
the story which I'll tell you
eventually in this talk
as I get farther will
be that
you know, if you can avoid
avoid using table to construct things.
or do operations, you're
probably going to be better off. So
Here's an example of a real table.
Okay, this is the Chebyshev note.
Okay.
and I've just done of the
fifth degree Chebyshev polynomial.
And let's check.
So we can check that
these actually are nodes by doing
the fall and we could do another table
that iterates over the
elements and a
table syntax, it iterates over the elements
of a vector
And it'll always treat this as a vaccine.
even if it's actually a deep
So you'll get list elements.
is I just
give the variable
And then instead of giving limits, I just give
of the table. It's the list
itself. Sure,
enough, they come out to be exactly Z.
0.
way of making a
a an array
which is often super useful
is to use outer problems.
And in this case, I'm doing this.
just the same
thing and I can
to do a list plot of out.
The trick is here that the dimensions of
this are so they're
And it mentions that a chevy-nep nodes for SIP
because there
you know, 6-6-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9-9
nodes to the actually I think I
an extra one that I didn't really need there.
That's repeated.
So it's 6-6. And then
the inner dimension
is this function while I'm creating a
list.
that makes an extra depth in
the array.
Now I want to talk about where do
where do arrays appear?
Okay. And it turns out that,
that are raised are basically,
And that's sort of the title of the talk.
Rays everywhere. Okay.
over the place.
very large array image.
Okay.
I can do a ray cure
of image data of image.
the image data, it
So the fundamental data behind this
is, and you can actually
actually get some more information
by looking at the,
image data
And it turns out, so it's,
So the image itself is $500.
177 by 1020.
for pixels.
And for each pixel, we have...
three color channels and an alpha channel.
And that's that four dimensions.
inner dimension is
is that alpha channel. And you can actually,
we change how those dimensions
by using the interleaving arm.
option of image.
So let's look at another example.
Here's our favorite, Spy
Um, so.
And this
doesn't look like an array at all.
and it's true it's not an
array, but the actual day
which is used to plot that and
stored in the polyhedron data is
So the coordinate cycle is the same.
which are the vertex groups,
coordinates you see aren't a
Okay.
And I can actually play with it.
this a little bit.
and get the maximum of the value.
value of the coordinates. So this goes up to two points.
Okay.
And then the cells,
themselves are an array.
actually the first element of the cells,
and it turns out that
that head of
cells is going to be
polygon. So these
So it's showing the actual
cells and this
graphics thing are
are polygons which give the faces.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
I'm going to play a little trick on spices.
with these spiky with these arrays.
by doing a
a transformation. So I'm going to get
So I made a mesh region.
of that, which is going to be
mesh region SPICe.
I'm gonna get the cells.
Okay. Now I'm going to, now what I'm
going to do. And here's another way of
affecting a transformation on a rate.
So the coordinates in an array, when I
What I'm saying is I'm going to map each element
element of the coordinates
So this works on the first level.
So each quarter is going to be
mapped by the coordinate time
it's norm minus three.
Okay.
to change the shape of the
coordinates, I'm going to basically remake
the mesh region with new coordinates and I guess
sort of a morphed
spiky by this this
operation. So this
This is the first example, which I'm really doing
operation on an array and
And map is a really useful...
one to do operations on a
Ray, there are more, and I'm
I'm going to show you ways to do operations
of an array as I get farther than I talk much, much faster.
Okay.
This is a really simple one.
I don't.
do an ND solve. So
all of these things are scalar. The,
the variable is scalar, but the actual way we
store the data for this is
an array and you can see each
element
every third, every other element
of the interpolating
function is an array. If you look at this input
form you can kind of see, well, the
This is the dimensions.
the limits, that's an array.
These are the coordinates and
And this is actually a special way of
storing the actual data and so that
it says packed and compacted.
as possible. So again,
Again, if you look inside of data,
return to you. Typically, there
there will be arrays and often you can translate
transform those arrays to change
the original object if you want.
In some cases, it's recommended.
it's not super recommended, but
um
Okay, so now let's talk about how
arrays are represented.
And this is probably the
the key topic
that you'll get something out of this whole
Okay.
Fundamental representation is a list
of lists of possibly lists
of lists, et cetera, et cetera. So,
Let's just take a matrix.
The full form is list to bliss.
list of list. Okay.
And if you go deeper, it's just...
just nested that much deeper.
enlist
Okay. And these are, these are each,
expressions or references to the elements.
Okay.
implicit and explicit, right?
There's a packed array.
representation, which is M
implicit okay so that's sort of
like, you know, the analogy for
that is I've got a friend with a
with a VWD
W. Vanagon, okay, and
And it looks like a Vanagon.
It looks like one of the original ones.
But somebody put a Ford engine
in it. Okay. So it actually goes
60 on the highway instead of like 405.
So,
So under the hood, it's different.
it actually looks the same externally.
And that's what a path array is.
Okay, now sparse arrays
are explicit
different.
representations that I'll get into.
An example of that is quantity array.
Other examples which we're starting to add
in development are structurally
structure matrices such as permutation
matrix block diagonal matrix.
And then we have a final type,
which is numeric array.
This allows you to work
with different types in the compiler
say for a GPU.
which might only support
at 32-bit floats instead of 6.5.
And I'll have an example.
that uses numeric array.
with the compiler eventually.
So
So let's look at packed array.
So let's do Red Hat.
This is a construction site.
of only a vector, so it's yet another
So this is, this is a,
is a packed array queue. So let's look at the
bite count, how much memory does that
Okay.
another way of doing
I'm going to take table,
Okay.
And the bike, if I just do that table, even
though the data itself is the same,
Okay.
the bite count is
is almost three times more.
And I can check that they're the same.
okay so they're
just like the look
is the same.
the actual storage on the system.
is
And you might ask, why doesn't table produce
because everything's integer.
is sort of a cryptic answer that
I'll show us a plot, okay?
well Avenge
the bike counter table goes way
down. And what happens is
above a certain size and that
limit actually happens to be 250.
we auto-compile the technology
when possible.
the compiler to generate
table and it not only generates it fast
but it generates a packed array out of it.
And so there are a number of
You can look at
If you look at compile options,
a bunch of blah, blah, blah,
including table compile links.
that give these limits.
And those can be quite useful.
we've
tried to set defaults that are appropriate.
but sometimes you may want to change those.
Okay.
the rate conversions. So this
developer two-factor
array converts to a packed array.
So if I have a mixed type,
Okay.
then I so so if
if I take this UA
So it has a...
a real element in an
integer element. Well, it doesn't pack on a
but you can specify coercion.
So if I say developer two-pack directories,
I want to coerce to reel.
It will go ahead and coerce to reel.
and generate a packed array.
Okay. And that's, um,
next.
And
yeah, if I convert from PAC to RA,
then it's not a packed rei anyway.
anymore, it's ordinary representation.
Okay, so let's take a
bigger packed array of
And let's compare. So we have a
packed array and an unpacked
array. And let's compare the
I mean, um,
And I almost always use repeat.
We needed timing to compare timings
Absolute timing usually doesn't
get enough information with
and the granularity.
So repeated time
I mean, there's a much more effective way to test time
me. Okay, so here
I
I did an outer product.
And if I do it with the packed arrays, it takes
takes 10 times less time
than doing it with the
unpacked arrays just because of the way
the operations were.
So if you can use packed arrays,
and operations like outer
or other things,
then you're going to have a much faster
to the master code.
And it gets even more extreme.
So there are methods.
Yeah.
to see if an operation has to unpack
actually works. So let's see.
So I've got...
unpacking gives this message.
because it's telling it's unpacking. And also
I would also say if I take map of some
arbitrary function F over that packed array,
Well, there's no way
the PAC to raise only work for, for,
fundamental machine types.
f of 1 is not a
fundamental machine type because it's sort
an arbitrary function, so it has to
So,
The messages are super useful, but they're going to be
irritating. So I'm going to turn them off for now.
So I'm going to
get to the next thing.
Here's a sparse array.
and
You can always...
So here we're talking about representations.
explicit and it shows it as a
sparse array. Okay, so
So the dense version of this,
is the normal
norm of the sparse arrays. This is
huge. It's kind of unwieldy
to look at, so I'm gonna delete that.
Okay.
I can do an operation.
now the
basically for representation,
representation, we say that, you know,
the operation
so that the sparse array
it represents zero.
So if you convert to normal,
be the same.
the actual objects are not the same.
So they're not same queue.
So what's the advantage of this?
sparse arrays? Well, again, it
It takes a lot less memory to use.
And there are many tasks
that are super effective
effective.
a linear algebra example.
again, I use
repeated timing. So,
The sparse array is very,
slightly faster.
bigger size.
with the same thing.
Now, this is a particularly simple case,
very advantageous to the sparse arithmetic.
Now I'm
I'm getting, you know, like almost
several hundred times
faster with a sparse array.
So, um,
so 200
250 times faster using the sparse
array. So for,
linear algebra tasks like
and efficient solving.
and the solvers that work on those.
So there's a representation.
contract and I'm explaining this for
sparse, but this is general for these things.
that we call array representations.
The idea is that normal,
of some operation of the
sparse array is equal to the
operation of normal
of sparse arrays.
Okay. Now, occasionally I use e-mail.
equal versus the same.
Because sometimes
like with numerical stuff, the error,
All of them are different. So the air may be
slightly different. But typically, this will be
the case. Okay. And here's two
examples of that.
thing to keep in mind.
So basically the operations
are effectively the same. They may be
done differently. They may be done more efficiently.
Okay.
So, these are structured representations.
new thing. Um,
They're different
representations based on structures.
So again, the structure
There's another array queue, array depth, dimension.
all work and again this
same contract. They operate
normal.
And when there's a special algorithm for operations,
It's used otherwise the representation
is typically converted to a different
representation for which there is an
So let's look at
an example.
So let's construct the quantity
array. Okay. And this is,
This is just kind of an
ordinary ray underneath
but the quantities are separate. So,
it's more
efficient. Here's the normal representation.
presentation.
of meters and then seconds.
So the
Big advantage of quant, one big advantage of quant
It's big memory savings.
So it's basically a factor of more than 10.
and memory savings
And then if there's a special algorithm,
there's a huge time saving.
Okay, so here's another example.
So
The quantity array takes
is 2020
times faster. Now notice the quantity
Quantity rate thing comes out as a quantity rate.
so it has this more efficient storage.
versus if I do the operation on the ordinary,
Ray, I get the list.
So again, it that
Depends what you want. But if you look at
these times.
Now numeric array is
is another type.
So here I can use integer 8
bit integers type.
If I do normal, I get a pack to
Ray.
So this again gives you
memory savings.
The trick about numerical arrays is
They're not considered a railroad.
representations. They're special and
interface to the compiler and
things like GPUs. So we
don't map and we actually
give a slightly
useful message saying we don't do traverse
Okay.
So this,
is a big part of
of working with arrays.
I'm going to give a bunch of examples.
arithmetic worked.
So if I take two matrices I made
symbolic if I add those
it does it element wise.
Okay. Here.
And if I add a vector to that,
It adds
the elements of the vectors by
row element wise.
Okay, now this doesn't work.
This case doesn't work with at length four.
because the way that...
that the default arithmetic works
is from the top down.
Engines have to match from the top down.
Now we've added recently a new thing
and I suggest you look up the
documentation for this. It's a nice example.
So threaded and what we're doing
And what this does is this says, OK,
I want to work from the bottom level
of the array.
And so it's,
it adds a V to
each of the columns versus
is adding it to the rows here.
So this threaded wire
wrapper allows you to do
which before were somewhat intangible.
and convenient. Okay. So the,
And the way this all works is through this
attribute called listability.
Okay. And I can set a
function to have the list of atrophy.
that thing. It applies effectively
to the elements.
OK, and again, I can do
you know, threaded V4
it applies to the elements.
Now, there's a huge
number of commands that are listable.
basically all the arithmetic,
You know, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
and that's a useful list to look
at if you want to get an idea of what
So let's look at this Chebyshev nodes that
example again. Okay, now I've
made them numerical so that
So there's even a fair comparison.
Okay, this takes a little bit.
So here I am.
I've done the Chebyshev nodes by using a
So the listable speech,
is tremendous.
us. So you're getting factors like
30 to 30 by you.
using the listable operation
versus the
the other operation.
Thank you.
you